Guide to the The Roy Vernon Sowers and Margaret Cosgrave Sowers papers, 1629-1994
Department of Special Collections
The Roy Vernon Sowers and Margaret Cosgrave Sowers papers,
1629-1994
M0888
Sowers, Margaret Cosgrave.
3.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
The collection contains items generated or received by either Margaret or both Roy and Margaret together. Includes many fine press examples, some personal correspondence, and library exhibit materials.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of the estate of Margaret Cosgrave Sowers, 1995.
Scope and Content
Items generated or received by either Margaret or both Roy and Margaret together. Includes many fine press examples, some personal correspondence, and library exhibit materials.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Archer, Richard.; Lewis, Blaine.; Powell, Lawrence Clark.; Rushmore, Arthur.; Rushmore, Edna.; Sowers, Margaret Cosgrave.; Sowers, Roy Vernon.; Stauffacher, Jack.; Straus, Norman.; Wilson, Adrian.; Alfred A. Knopf.; Allen Press.; Angel Alley Press.; Anvil Press.; Arizona Pioneers Historical Society.; Arthur Lites Press.; Bird and Bull Press.; Black Vine Press.; Blackwood Press.; Book Club of California.; Brick Row Book Shop.; Carl Herzog Press.; Castle Press.; Centaur Press.; Colt Press.; Cooper Square Publishers.; Crompton T. Johnson.; Dawson's Bookshop.; Grabhorn Press.; Innominate Press.; Laboratory Press.; Lime Kiln Press.; Pynson Printers.; Ward Ritchie Press.; Windsor Press.; Zeitlin and Ver Brugge.; Book collecting--California.; Booksellers and bookselling--California.; Libraries--California.; Printing.
Collection Contents
- Series 1. Christmas Cards/ Personal Correspondence
  - Blaine Lewis/Innominate Press; Arthur Rushmore/Edna Rushmore (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Norman Straus; Stauffacher (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - various Christmas cards and personal correspondence (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Christmas and New Years cards. 1872, 1873., 43 items. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series 2. Inauguration of F.W. Ness as President of Fresno State College
  - 2 items printed by Ward Ritchie Press (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series 3. Rollins College, Winter Park, Florida, Rollins College Department of Books, and Angel Alley Press materials
  - Angel Alley Press (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fight of a Book for the World (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Inadvisability of Arriving at Conclusions (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Songs of A Day (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lyric Heart (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - A Professor of Books (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Town that became a University (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Rollins' Slant on Creative Writing / by Edwin Osgood Grover (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - announcement of courses in the appreciation and use of books, Rollins College, 3 small items (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series 4. Lawrence Clark Powell -see also oversized materials
  - Writings about librarianship: The Alchemy of Books; This Dry and Wrinkled Land; Land of Fiction; Sky, Sun, and Water, the Southwest of Frederick Webb Hodges (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Publications: The Three L's; In Search of Spring; William Andrews Clark Memorial Library Welcoming Address; Recollections of an ex-bookseller; Aldous Huxley (2 copies); Trans Pecos; Bent's Fort. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Los Angeles Printing: 8 items by LCP or printed "for the Friends of LCP." (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Laboratory Press at the Carnegie Institute of Technology (Box 1, Folder 11)
    2 items from Jack Stauffacher, who was director of the New Laboratory Press.
- Series 5. Exhibit Materials
  - Exhibit Announcements: 10 items from exhibits at: the Huntington Library, Library of Congress, American Institute of Graphic Arts, Book Club of California, Williams College, Schaeffer Galleries. (1928-1970) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Exhibit Publications: 5 items from exhibits at: Williams College, John Henry Nash Library (Aldine Press), UC Santa Cruz (Thomas Carlyle), Royal Academy Diploma Gallery (1935-1970), University of Michigan Clements Library (Presbyterian Church in America, 1947) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Exhibit Publications: 4 items from exhibits at: UCLA Clark Memorial Library, National Arts Club, Huntington Library, Colorado College. (1936-1967). (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Exhibits - Stanford Libraries: 13 items: John Steinbeck (1975), Gunst Collection (1963), Eric Gill (1954), Colt Press (1956), John Cole (1982), Ansel Adams and W. Stegner (1982), F.L. Wright (1981), California as seen by German Travellers (1980), W. Somerset Maugham (1979), Broad Pen... Lecture (1979), Magna Carta (1978), Green Library Dedication (1980). (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series 6. Prospectus from Fine Presses and Book shops - see also oversized materials
  - A-C, (19 items): (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Adrian Wilson, Alfred A. Knopf, Anvil Press, Arizona Pioneers Historical Society, Arthur Lites Press, Bird and Bull Press, Black Vine Press, Blackwood Press, Book Club of California, Brick Row Book Shop, Carl Herzog Press, Centaur Press, Colt Press/Jane Grabhorn, Cooper Square Publishers, Crompton T. Johnson
  - Allen Press (8 items, c. 1953-1973) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - D-H (17 items): (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Dawson's Bookshop, Delhagen & Klafings Monatscheft,, Edizioni il Polifilo, Milan, Edwin A.R. Rumball-Petr, Eugrammia Press, Evergreen House Foundation, Folio Society,London,
  - Golden Head Press (5 items, c. 1962-1965) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Grabhorn Press (2 items, c.1953) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Greenwood Press/J. Stauffacher, (5 items) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - J-Penguin, ( 9 items): (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Jake Zeitlin, John Henry Nash, Lakeside Press, Lawton Kennedy, Publisher, Lime Kiln Press, New York Public Library, Pantheon Books, Penguin Press
  - Porpoise Book shop (4 items, c. 1950s) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Peter Pauper-S, (9 items): (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Peter Pauper Press, Pox Populi Press, Prairie Press, Random House/Nonesuch Press, Sacramento Book Collector's Club, Sequoia Press, "The Studio", Sumac Press
  - T-Z, (18 items): (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Talisman Press, Toz House Bookshop, Trianon Press, United Efforts Press, University of California Press, Verlag Muller & Schindler, W. Thomas Taylor, Wallace Kibbee & Son, Wilgress Press, William Edwin Rudge, Windsor Press (-see oversize material), Wm. Dawson, World Publishing Co., Yale University Press, Year of Dog Press, Yolla Bolly Press, Zamarano Club
  - Ward Ritchie Press, (6 items) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Stanford University Libraries Annual Reports1973-74, 1974-75 - (Box 3, Folder 7)
    include items donated by MCS
  - Gleeson Library Associates Materials 16 items, ca. 1978-1990: (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Nicolai Rezanov & Concepcion Arguello, Fall meeting, 1993; Forgeries in the Rare Book World, Autumn meeting, 1990; Hans Schmoller, announcement for Autumn Lecture 1978; Lilienthal Collections exhibit, 1978; Filoli Spring Tour, 1979; John Dreyfus, announcement for annual meeting, 1979; Albert Speirsen exhibit, 1979; Annual meeting announcements, 1979, 1980, 1981; Willa Cather lecture announcement and program, Winter, 1978; Winter meeting, 1979; Autumn meeting programs, 1980, 1981
- Series 7. Fine Press Publications
  - Benjamin Franklin on the art of eating (Princeton University Press for the American Philosophical Society, 1958) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Is there a Santa Claus? (Grosset & Dunlap, 1934) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Journey to Truckee (Elkus Press, 1945) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Ritchie, Ward, William Morris and his Praise of Wine (Ward Ritchie Press, 1958) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Stevenson, R.L., Silverado Squatters, the introductory chapter (Kit-Cat Press, 1988) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "These are the times that try men's souls" ( University of Michigan, 1942 -, 2 copies). (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Introduction to Ben Johnson's "Three Masques" (W.C. Bamburgh, Presentation copy no. 18/39) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Lincoln, Abraham, An Appreciation of Thomas Jefferson (Wallace Kibbee & Son, 1937) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Magee, David, Chapter II of an unpublished autobiography (Sherwood Grover, 1979 -, 2 copies) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Territory of Utah, (Westgate Press, 1951) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Turner Thesis and the dry world (Texas Western Press, 1960) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Allen Press 2 items (c. 1950s): (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Shelley, Percy Bysshe, Ode to the West Wind;Letter with enclosed broadside, "With no raison d'être but instead of a letter."
  - Blackwood Press, 5 items: (Box 4, Folder 4)
    A Collection of Maxims and Aphorisms and 4 menus from the annual banquets of the Sacramento Society for Medical Improvement.
  - Roxburghe, Zamorano, and Rounce & Coffin Materials - see also oversized materials, 3 items: (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Rounce and Coffin Club Hog and Book Auction program; A Self Portrait of Captain Agustin V. Zamorano; Roxburghe Club of San Francisco, Zamorano Club of Los Angeles, 1955
- Series 8. Publications about Books, Book Collecting, Binding
  - ABC Keepsake. Oxford University Press, 1944. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Anatomy of a Library, Sutro Library, San Francisco. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Book Collecting Should be Fun, by Frederic C. Melcher. Sheboygan, Elm City Press, 1947. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Chief End of Book Madness, by L. C. Wroth. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Editing Donne and Pope. William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, lecture program, 1952. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Fifty Books of the Year 1948, New York: American Institute of Graphic Arts, 1948. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - First Annual Report of The Vancouver Bookshop and Fun in a Bookshop, Vancouver Bookship. signed. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - For Further Reading, compiled by Willard Smith, Mills College: Eucalyptus Press, 1935. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Journey to Truckee, Berkeley: The Elkus Press, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - My Ten-Cent Shelf, by Mitchell Kennerly, Clements Library reprint from March 1944 American Mercury. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Olive Percival Collection of Children's Books, UCLA. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Revelations of Two Celebrated Book-Snatchers or, What Victoria Read - the Sadleir Collection, Friends of the UCLA library,1953. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Western Books 1946, 1947. LA: Rounce and Coffin Club. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series 9. Publications of the Book Trade
  - Taylor & Taylor insert to Annual of Bookmaking, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Fine Print (III:4, Oct. 1977) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Dolphin Review of Fine Printing (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Journal of the Rutgers University Library (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 500 Years of Printing, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Bohemian Club Library Notes, Summer 1993 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - California Society of Etchers, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Colophon Crier, Sept., May, Dec. 1932 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - E Clampus Vitus, announcement (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Hoja Volante, Zamarano Cub, Nov. 1950 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Imprimatur, I:1, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Notes on Printing & Graphic Arts, Stinehour Press, I:3, II:1-2. 1953-54 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Esto Publishing Co. "Enjoy Your Museum Series", 16 pamphlets and 1 prosectus. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    II: Prints was written by Roy and Pauline Sowers
- Series 10. Typography Examples
  - "The Pleasures of Study," Anatomy of Melancholy, R. Burton, UCLA Clark Library (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Songs of Innocence," William Blake, 1795? (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Morley on the Prenatal Word," 1940, (tiny book in envelope) (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - unbound signatures for Charaters, or Essayers,... by R.M., 1629. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Tribute to Albert M. Bender, Book Club of California, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Response cards to the Roxburghe Club, SF, by Grabhorn Printing, S. Grover (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Andreae Vesalii, publication offer (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Oscar Lewis (President of Book Club of California) autographed letter to RVS, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Wilder Bentley, Archetype Press Prospectus, Berkeley, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Arthur Rushmore autographed note (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Pynson Printers, 10 Announcements, 1930-34 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sumac Press, example (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - The Friendly hen, broadside (2 copies) (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Evelyn Hassbaum, 2 examples of work (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Series 11. Oversized materials
  - Greenwood Press, Taylor & Taylor Printers, Windsor Press, Golden Cockerel Press, McKenzie & Harris, Inc. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Unidentified Ledgers, 2 items (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Items from Travels6 items:, Museum Plantin-Moretus, Antwerp; Trinity College, Cambridge; Austrian National Library, Vienna; Biblioteca Riccardiana, Florence; map of Venice and Murano (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Lawrence Clark Powell - oversized materials2 items:, "Brush Country" and "What we are here for" printed for the Friends of LCP. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "Safety First" Calendar, the Curwen Press (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Roxburghe Club Materials, 7 items: (Box 5, Folder 8)
    mostly meeting announcements